<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Personal Webpage</title>
    <link>https://andreas.oslandsbotn.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Personal Webpage</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://andreas.oslandsbotn.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>MSc in Applied Physics</title>
      <link>https://andreas.oslandsbotn.com/experience/master/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://andreas.oslandsbotn.com/experience/master/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;thesis--summary&#34;&gt;Thesis — Summary&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Developed a gradient-based shape optimisation framework combined with the multimesh finite element method, avoiding costly re-meshing of moving objects.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Derived a novel analytical shape gradient for the Stokes-drag problem using the adjoint approach and Hadamard’s theorem.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Validated the method numerically, demonstrating accurate gradients near extrema and competitive performance on relevant benchmarks.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;master-of-science--summary&#34;&gt;Master of Science — Summary&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Specialization optimization and mathematical modeling&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Average grade: A&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;subjects&#34;&gt;Subjects&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Optimization&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;ODEs &amp;amp; PDEs&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Mathematical Analysis, Linear Algebra, Calculus&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Physics: Optics, Classical Mechanics, Quantum Mechanics, Electromagnetism&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Technical Intern</title>
      <link>https://andreas.oslandsbotn.com/experience/neo/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://andreas.oslandsbotn.com/experience/neo/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As part of the hyperspectral imaging group at Norsk Elektro Optikk, I worked on improving image quality and signal robustness in their hyperspectral camera systems.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Designed and evaluated low-pass and band-limited filters to improve signal quality&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Used Fourier analysis to identify camera and sensor related issues&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Technical Intern</title>
      <link>https://andreas.oslandsbotn.com/experience/cern/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://andreas.oslandsbotn.com/experience/cern/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As part of the TE-MPE Department (Magnet Protection &amp;amp; Electrical Integrity), I contributed to experimental work supporting the HiLumi upgrade of the LHC.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Designed and built an experiment to study proton-beam effects on superconducting magnets&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Planned the setup and produced CAD designs in collaboration with CERN’s mechanical workshop&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Assembled, executed, and analyzed the experiment, including PXI-based sensor data acquisition&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PhD Candidate in Computer Science</title>
      <link>https://andreas.oslandsbotn.com/experience/phd/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://andreas.oslandsbotn.com/experience/phd/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Supervisors: Prof. Alexander Cloninger, Dr. Zeljko Kereta &amp;amp; Dr. Nickolas Forsch&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;My PhD focused on developing scalable and reliable learning algorithms for large, high-dimensional datasets, with an emphasis on streaming and parallelization.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Grounded in statistical learning theory, I designed learning methods that reformulate classical algorithms into multi-resolution and boosting-style frameworks, enabling efficient training and inference under realistic memory and compute limits. Key contributions include:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;StreaMRAK: A multi-resolution, boosting-based learning framework supporting streaming data and adaptive model complexity&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Visiting Research Scholar</title>
      <link>https://andreas.oslandsbotn.com/experience/ucsd/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://andreas.oslandsbotn.com/experience/ucsd/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Supervisor: Prof. Alexander cloninger&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As part of my PhD I completed a Research stay at UCSD working with Prof. Alexander Cloninger and Prof. Yoav Freund, the main focus was scalable representation learning for high-dimensional data.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Developed methods for low-dimensional representations that preserve local structure while remaining computationally scalable&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Developed a graph-based embedding approach that scales to large datasets through localization and parallelization, avoiding the quadratic complexity of classical spectral methods&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Machine Learning Engineer</title>
      <link>https://andreas.oslandsbotn.com/experience/optoscale/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://andreas.oslandsbotn.com/experience/optoscale/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;responsibilities--progression&#34;&gt;Responsibilities &amp;amp; progression&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jan. 2025 – present&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&lt;em&gt;Lead development of automatic feeding system&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;In charge of system-level planning and architecture&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Worked with YOLO and MoViNet to develop machine vision algorithms&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Developed Object tracking alogrithm for video streams&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Deployed and maintained models and services on production hardware&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jun. 2024 – Dec. 2024&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&lt;em&gt;Machine learning infrastructure and efficiency&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Improved model efficiency and evaluation pipelines&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Developed and maintained data pipelines&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Strengthened CI/CD for ML workflows&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Education</title>
      <link>https://andreas.oslandsbotn.com/education/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://andreas.oslandsbotn.com/education/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Education blabla&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;PhD in Mathematics&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Machine Learning &amp;amp; Computer Vision&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Applied research in aquaculture systems&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effective resistance in metric spaces</title>
      <link>https://andreas.oslandsbotn.com/publications/erms-2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://andreas.oslandsbotn.com/publications/erms-2023/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Effective resistance (ER) is an attractive way to interrogate the structure of graphs. It is an alternative to computing the eigenvectors of the graph Laplacian. One attractive application of ER is to point clouds, i.e. graphs whose vertices correspond to IID samples from a distribution over a metric space. Unfortunately, it was shown that the ER between any two points converges to a trivial quantity that holds no information about the graph’s structure as the size of the sample increases to infinity. In this study, we show that this trivial solution can be circumvented by considering a regionbased ER between pairs of small regions rather than pairs of points and by scaling the edge weights appropriately with respect to the underlying density in each region. By keeping the regions fixed, we show analytically that the region-based ER converges to a non-trivial limit as the number of points increases to infinity. Namely the ER on a metric space. We support our theoretical findings with numerical experiments.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Impact of 440 GeV Proton beams on Superconductors in a Cryogenic Environment</title>
      <link>https://andreas.oslandsbotn.com/publications/beam-impact-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://andreas.oslandsbotn.com/publications/beam-impact-2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The superconducting magnets used in high energy particle accelerators such as CERN’s LHC can be impacted by the circulating beam in case of specific failures. This leads to interaction of the beam particles with the magnet components, like the superconducting coils, through direct beam impact or via secondary particle showers. The interaction causes energy deposition in the timescale of microseconds and induces large thermal gradients within the superconductors, which are in the order of 100 K/mm. To investigate the effect on the superconductors, an experiment at CERN’s HiRadMat facility was designed and executed, exposing short samples of Nb-Ti and Nb3Sn strands in a cryogenic environment to microsecond 440 GeV proton beams. The irradiated samples were extracted and analyzed for their critical transport current Ic. This paper describes the results and analysis of the measurements of Ic as well as thermo-mechanical simulations of the Nb3Sn strands to evaluate the degradation of Ic as a function of the mechanical strain present during and after the beam impact.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improving inversion of model parameters from action potential recordings with kernel methods</title>
      <link>https://andreas.oslandsbotn.com/publications/ap-inversion-2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://andreas.oslandsbotn.com/publications/ap-inversion-2023/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Current methods for solving inverse problems in cardiac electrophysiology are limited by their accuracy, scalability, practicality, or a combination of these. In this proof-of-concept study we demonstrate the feasibility of using kernel methods to solve the inverse problem of estimating the parameters of ionic membrane currents from observations of corresponding action potential (AP) traces. In particular, we consider AP traces generated by a cardiac cell action potential model, which mimics those obtained experimentally in measurable in vitro cardiac systems. Using synthetic training data from the 1977 Beeler-Reuter AP model of mammalian ventricular cardiomyocytes, we demonstrate our recently proposed boosted kernel ridge regression (KRR) solver StreaMRAK, which is particularly robust and well-adapted for high-complexity functions. We show that this method is less memory demanding, estimates the model parameters with higher accuracy, and is less exposed to parameter sensitivity issues than existing methods, such as standard KRR solvers and loss-minimization schemes based on nearest-neighbor heuristics.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Random walks, conductance, and resistance for the connection graph Laplacian</title>
      <link>https://andreas.oslandsbotn.com/publications/cgraphlp-2024/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://andreas.oslandsbotn.com/publications/cgraphlp-2024/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We investigate the concept of effective resistance in connection graphs, expanding its traditional application from undirected graphs. We propose a robust definition of effective resistance in connection graphs by focusing on the duality of Dirichlet type and Poisson-type problems on connection graphs. Additionally, we delve into random walks, taking into account both node transitions and vector rotations. This approach introduces novel concepts of effective conductance and resistance matrices for connection graphs, capturing mean rotation matrices corresponding to random walk transitions. Thereby, it provides new theoretical insights for network analysis and optimization.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>StreaMRAK - Streaming Multi-Resolution Adaptive Kernel Algorithm</title>
      <link>https://andreas.oslandsbotn.com/publications/streamrak-2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://andreas.oslandsbotn.com/publications/streamrak-2022/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Kernel ridge regression (KRR) is a popular scheme for non-linear non-parametric learning. However, existing implementations of KRR require that all the data is stored in the main memory, which severely limits the use of KRR in contexts where data size far exceeds the memory size. Such applications are increasingly common in data mining, bioinformatics, and control. A powerful paradigm for computing on data sets that are too large for memory is the streaming model of computation, where we process one data sample at a time, discarding each sample before moving on to the next one. In this paper, we propose StreaMRAK - a streaming version of KRR. StreaMRAK improves on existing KRR schemes by dividing the problem into several levels of resolution, which allows continual refinement to the predictions. The algorithm reduces the memory requirement by continuously and efficiently integrating new samples into the training model. With a novel sub-sampling scheme, StreaMRAK reduces memory and computational complexities by creating a sketch of the original data, where the sub-sampling density is adapted to the bandwidth of the kernel and the local dimensionality of the data. We present a showcase study on two synthetic problems and the prediction of the trajectory of a double pendulum. The results show that the proposed algorithm is fast and accurate.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Structure from Voltage</title>
      <link>https://andreas.oslandsbotn.com/publications/sfv-2026/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://andreas.oslandsbotn.com/publications/sfv-2026/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;One of the major challenges in data science is the analysis of large point clouds in high dimensional metric spaces. Fortunately, many of these datasets are concentrated around low-dimensional manifolds. This, in principle, allows computation and reduced dimensionality that scales with the intrinsic, rather than the ambient dimension. The large and growing field of non-linear dimensionality reduction (NLDR) aims to develop algorithms that take advantage of low intrinsic dimension in datasets, both for visualization and for developing a low-dimensional coordinate system for downstream analysis. NLDR ranges from mathematically rigorous methods such as Laplacian Eigenmaps (Belkin and Niyogi, 2003, 2008) and Difusion maps (Coifman et al., 2005) that scale like (O(n^2)) with n points, to methods such as t-SNE (Van der Maaten and Hinton, 2008) and UMAP (McInnes et al., 2018) that are much more efficient but have weak mathematical foundation and guarantees. In this paper, we propose a scalable NLDR strategy we call Localized Voltage Maps (LVM). Our method is based on the Laplacian framework but in a way thats easily parallelizable and scalable to large data sets. The augmentations come from using inhomogeneous, rather than homogeneous, solutions of the Laplacian, and by adding a special ground vertex to the graph thats an absorbing state for random walks. Our method also generates a hierarchical set of coordinates, where one can zoom-in on a subset of the data and compute a local coordinate system that best characterizes the data in that region, without having to recompute the embedding from scratch. We describe an implementation of this algorithm and demonstrate its effectiveness on MNIST and on the GloVe/wiki word-vector database.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
